Guide to the Bowers Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bowers family papers
1859-1910
MS 1194
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
The papers contain correspondence, notes, and reports on politics in Connecticut and New Hampshire during the Reconstruction Era, forestry and timber lands, and Yale alumni activities in Washington, D.C., plus a small collection of autograph letters and clipped signatures.
Bowers family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In part transferred from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Bowers Family Papers are contained in one box and include alphabetically arranged correspondence plus reports, notes, and bills on forestry and the preservation of forest lands. The collection spans the dates 1859 – 1910 and consists of two groups of material. The first is the papers of Edward Augustus Bowers and the second is the Bowers Papers transferred from Beinecke Rare Books Library in February 1984.
Correspondence, folders 1-13, consists of letters primarily written to Caleb Bailey Bowers (1820 – 1898) and two of his sons, Edward Augustus Bowers (1857 – 1924) and Dwight Eliot Bowers (1866 – 1907). For biographical information see Edward E. Atwater's History of the City of New Haven (1887), pp. 343-45; on Edward A. Bowers see Obituary Record of Yale Graduates, 1924 – 1925, pp. 1343-45; and on Dwight E. Bowers the Obituary Record of Graduates, 1906 – 07, pp. 769-70.
The Bowers Papers contain some sixty letters to Caleb B. Bowers on politics in New Hampshire and Connecticut during the Civil War and reconstruction eras. Bowers lived in New Hampshire in 1866-7, was an active supporter of the reconstruction policies of President Andrew Johnson, and was elected a delegate to the National Union Convention of Internal Revenue for the third district of New Hampshire as a reward for his loyalty. Bowers' New Hampshire correspondents in 1866-7 include Charles Jacob Amidon, Edmund Burke, Micajah Currier Burleigh, Joshua D. Colony, William Huse Cummings, Edward Stearns Cutler, Daniel Marcy, and Don Houston Woodward. Except for his brief stay in New Hampshire, Bowers spent most of his life in Connecticut and information on politics in the state for the period 1862-68 can be found in the correspondence of Roger Averill, James Dixon, and Thomas A. Hendricks. In 1868, for example, Bowers stated that Hendricks was likely to receive the support of a majority of the state's delgation to the Democratic Convention.
For several years in the early 1890's Edward A. Bowers was an officer in the Yale Alumni Association of Washington, D.C. Approximately twenty letters, mostly written between 1892 and 1894, concern this subject. The collection also includes autograph correspondence. It contains letters written by Admiral George Dewey, Stephen J. Field, John Marshall Harlan, Joseph R. Hawley, Rutherford B. Hayes, Theodore Roosevelt, and Alfred H. Terry, plus a folder containing clipped autograph signatures. The Bowers Family Papers also contain material on forestry and timber lands dating from the years 1885-94, when Edward A. Bowers was inspector of the Public Land Service, assistant commissioner of the General Land Office, and an attorney in Washington, D.C.
Biographical / Historical
Caleb Bailey Bowers (1820-1898): a Connecticut native; was a businessman who was active in Democratic Party politics.
Edward Augustus Bowers (1857-1924): son of Caleb B. Bowers; was an early advocate of forest conservation.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forest policy; Forestry law and legislation; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; New Hampshire -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1877; Autographs; Politicians; Amidon, Charles Jacob, 1827-1900; Bowers family; Bowers, Caleb Bailey, 1820-1898; Bowers, Dwight Eliot, 1866-1907; Bowers, Edward A. (Edward Augustus), 1857-1924; Burke, Edmund, 1809-1882; Burleigh, Micajah Currier, 1818-1881; Cutter, Edward Stearns, 1822-1903; Dixon, James, 1814-1873; Hendricks, Thomas A. (Thomas Andrews), 1819-1885; Marcy, Daniel, 1809-1893; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Woodward, Don Houston, 1835-1908; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Correspondence A, 1863-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence B, 1866-1900, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence C, 1866-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence D, 1862-1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence E -F, 1888-1899, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence G -J, 1866-1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence L -M, 1866-1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence N -P, 1859-1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence R, 1866-1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence S, 1892-1903 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence T, 1867-1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence V -Y, 1866-1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Autograph signatures, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Quill pen from estate of Senator Samuel Clarke Pomeroy, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Draft reports on forestry, 1886-1894, n.s. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Status of proposed forestry reservations, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Timber Report of 1887 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes on forestry, 1889-1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - House and Senate bills on forestry, 1885-1894 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes on the protection and administration of forests in the public domain, 1885-1894, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lewis and Clarke Preserve, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - U.S. government publications, 1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brochures from western resorts, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)